<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- IN BEARBEITUNG von FZ, 20.02.2015 -->
<?xml-model href="../WvH_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de"
     telota:doctype="wvh_letters">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Marsden an Wilhelm von Humboldt, 21.05.1831<idno type="BBAW">415</idno>
            </title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/135657458">Frank Zimmer</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/120492644">Jürgen Trabant</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/1053159110">Ute Tintemann</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6587-3353">Lou Klappenbach</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7447-4589">Sascha Grabsch</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Elise Hanrahan</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <title>Wilhelm von Humboldt: Online-Edition der sprachwissenschaftlichen Korrespondenz</title>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de">
                    Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften (BBAW)
                </ref>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="orig">Grundlage der Edition: Ehem. Preußische Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, gegenwärtig
                            in der Jagiellonen-Bibliothek Krakau, Coll. ling. fol. 53, Bl.
                            176–179</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="print"/>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="KMV">S. 223</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="Mattson"/>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
            <listPerson type="mentioned">
               <person corresp="cbrosses">
                  <persName>Brosses, Charles de</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="tsraffles">
                  <persName>Raffles, Sir Thomas Stamford</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="gerumpf">
                  <persName>Rumpf (Rumphius), Georg Eberhard</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="fvalentijn">
                  <persName>Valentijn, François</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listBibl type="mentioned">
               <bibl corresp="948">Collectanea malaica vocabularia: Hoc est congeries omnium
                    dictionariorum malaicorum: hactenus editorum (Batavia: Apud Andream Lambertum
                    Loderum 1707)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="699">Marsden, William: A Grammar of the Malayan language, with an
                    introduction and praxis (London: Cox &amp; Baylis 1812)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="958">Marsden, William: Bibliotheca Marsdeniana philologica et
                    orientalis. A catalogue of books and manuscripts collected with a view to the
                    general comparison of languages, and to the study of Oriental literature
                    (London: J. L. Cox 1827)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="350">Raffles, Sophia: Memoir of the Life and Public Services of Sir
                    Thomas Stamford Raffles (London: John Murray 1830)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="351">Raffles, Thomas Stamford: The History of Java. In two Volumes
                    (London: Black, Parbury, and Allen 1817)</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <ab type="incipit">My dear Sir. Before I proceed to reply to your Queries
                        …</ab>
         </abstract>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName key="wmarsden">Marsden, William</persName>
               <date type="author" when="1831-05-21"/>
               <placeName key="London">London</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName key="wvh">Humboldt, Wilhelm von</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <ref target="350" type="prev">02.04.1831</ref>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote scribe="wmarsden">Eigenhändig</handNote>
         </handNotes>
         <langUsage n="ind">
            <language ident="kaw">Kawi</language>
            <language ident="ms">Malaiisch</language>
            <language ident="pi">Pali</language>
            <language ident="sa">Sanskrit</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <list>
            <item n="name">FZ</item>
            <item n="date">20. Februar 2015</item>
            <item n="status">in Bearbeitung</item>
         </list>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_353.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_354.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_355.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_356.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_357.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_358.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_359.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831-05-21/Coll.ling.fol.53_360.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <pb n="176r"/>
               <dateline>London 21.<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> May 1831</dateline>
               <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Before I proceed to reply to your Queries, allow me to express my best thanks for
                    the very kind &amp; handsome terms in which you speak of my literary labours. I
                    can only say that during the long period of half a century that has elapsed
                    since I first ventured to publish, they have always been directed to the
                    investigation &amp; establishment of Truth.</p>
            <p>In the first place you state that „<persName ref="tsraffles">M.
                        Raffles</persName> tâche de prouver dans une lettre qu’il vous a adressé en
                    1815 et qui se trouve dans <bibl sameAs="350">les Mémoires de sa vie</bibl>, que
                    les rapports avec le continent de l’Inde et la civilisation qui en a été la
                    suite, se sont établis plus tôt dans les îles Moluques qu’à <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName>. Il dit à la
                    suite de ce raisonnement (<bibl sameAs="350">p. 237</bibl>) que le Malay le plus
                    cultivé (car c’est ainsi que je comprends l’expression <hi rend="underline">the
                        highest Malay</hi>) est parlé dans les îles Moluques, et que la traduction
                    de la Bible <del>dont <persName ref="tsraffles">S.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                            Thomas Raffles</persName> parle</del> dans ce langage est à peine
                    (scarcely) <hi rend="underline">intelligible</hi> à ceux qui habitent les îles
                    situées plus vers l’Ouest. Je servis curieux de connoitre, Monsieur, votre
                    opinion sur ce passage et notamment sur les questions suivantes:“</p>
            <p>Upon this I have to observe that the fact of the <pb n="176v"/> people of the
                    Molucca islands having been civilised by intercourse with the continent of India
                    at a more early period than those of <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName>, does not appear to me, from what I
                    know of those islands, to be well founded, nor is it probable in itself.
                    Splendid remains of Indian temples, with their numerous deities, still exist in
                    the latter great island, &amp; one of its dialects consists almost wholly of
                    Hindu, <hi rend="underline">Pali</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Kawi</hi> words;
                    but we have no evidence of the like being noticed in Ceram, Banda, or Amboyna.
                    Their spices, it is true, have been objects of luxury in the West from the
                    remotest times; yet it is more likely that <subst>
                  <del>they</del>
                  <add>these</add>
               </subst> were collected at different <hi rend="underline">Emporia</hi>, &amp;
                    from thence procured by vessels from India, the Persian Gulf, &amp; the Red Sea,
                    than that the trade was a direct one to the remote islands where they were
                    produced. It is true that since the period at which the Eastern archipelago has
                    fallen under the dominion of Europeans, the progress of Christianity &amp; the
                    degree of civilisation attending it has been much more considerable in the
                    smaller islands, such as the Moluccas, than in the larger, where the native
                    population is comparatively independent; but this foreign influence has
                    certainly not had the effect of redering the Malayan dialect more pure. Of the
                    contrary we find a proof in the „<bibl sameAs="948">Collectanea Malaica
                        Vocabularia</bibl>“ published at <placeName ref="Batavia">Batavia</placeName> in 1707, where a list is given of „Eenighe Portuguysche
                    woorden die inde Eylanden van Amboyna, Banda, en Molucken veel onder ’t Maleys
                    werden vermenght“; amounting in number to 143. This, however, is to be
                    understood of the common oral dialects, from which the written language varies
                    much, although <pb n="177r"/> not essentially different. The latter preserves an
                    uniformity, &amp; the reading of a letter from a prince of <hi rend="underline">Ternate</hi> is attended with no more difficulty than of one from the
                    peninsula of Malacca. „High Malays“ may therefore be described as the language
                    of the best literary composition, of the courts, &amp; of the superior class of
                    people, as distinguished from the vulgar idiom of small traders, servants, &amp;
                    others of the lower class – which, in truth, is that of the generality of
                    Europeans.</p>
            <p>You then ask: 1.° „Quelle est la traduction de la Bible dont <persName ref="tsraffles">S.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thomas Raffles</persName>
                    parle? J’en trouve plusieurs dans <bibl sameAs="958">le Catalogue de votre
                        bibliothèque</bibl>, mais n’en connois par moi-même que celle publiée
                    récemment en lettres Romaines par la Societé biblique.“</p>
            <p>It is difficult to say to which of the Translations <persName ref="tsraffles">S.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> T. S. Raffles</persName> meant to
                    refer, but I consider as decidedly the best, that which was printed at
                        <placeName ref="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</placeName> in the year 1732, II vols.
                        4.<hi rend="superscript">to</hi>, in a modified Roman character, &amp; of
                    which an Edition in the Malayan character was printed at <placeName ref="Batavia">Batavia</placeName> in 1758, V. vols. 8.<hi rend="superscript">vo</hi>. No evidence appears of this translation having been prepared in a
                    dialect peculiar to the Molucca islands, nor, as the style adopted is that of
                    the High or literary, do I think that any distinction of dialect could be
                    observed. The Ecclesiatics to whose pious labours we are indebted for the work,
                    were liable, like other servants of the <orgName ref="11">East India
                        Company</orgName>, to be removed from place to place, &amp; it is not
                    improbable that more leisure or freedom from interruption may have been found at
                    Amboyna than at <placeName ref="Batavia">Batavia</placeName>.</p>
            <p>2.° „Cette traduction dont <persName ref="tsraffles">Raffles</persName> parle,
                    diffère-t-elle en effet si fort pour le langage du Malay tel que Vous l’avez
                    donné <pb n="177v"/> dans <bibl sameAs="699">votre Grammaire</bibl>, ou est-ce
                    que <persName ref="tsraffles">Sir Thomas</persName> a voulu dire seulement que
                    ce langage ressemble précisement trop au langage cultivé de Malacca pour être
                    facilement compris par les personnes accoutumées aux dialectes vulgaires des
                    îles plus vers l’Ouest, tandis qu’aux Moluques il est familier au peuple
                    même?“</p>
            <p>This is in great measure answered by what I have said above, &amp; it is only
                    necessary to add, that persons who have acquired a competent knowledge of the
                    Malayan language for the ordinary transactions of business, might still find
                    themselves at a loss in the perusal of this version, &amp; would be disposed to
                    attribute the difficulty of its being composed in the dialect of some remote
                    place; &amp;, in fact, this superior style has been objected to by some
                    preachers of the Gospel, as ill-suited to the generality of their congregations,
                    which consist of the lower classes of people, to whom the other versions were
                    more practically useful.</p>
            <p>3.° „Si ce langage des Moluques diffère de celui de Malacca, est-ce dans les mots
                    seulement, nommément dans un plus grand nombre de mots sanscrits, ou est-ce
                    aussi dans les formes grammaticales? – Ce point est surtout d’une grande
                    importance.“</p>
            <p>The style employed in good writings &amp; by well-educated persons, in
                    conversation (but without any particular reference to the Molucca islands) does
                    contain a greater number of words derived from the Sanskrit, &amp; works on
                    religious <pb n="178r"/> subjects, a much greater number of Arabic words, than
                    occur in the common language; but the difference is not <sic>fundemental</sic>;
                    any more than is that which arises from a greater degree of precision in the
                    grammatical forms or mode of employing the prefixed &amp; affixed particles,
                    answering the purpose of the Latin inflexions.</p>
            <p>4.° „Je n’ai presque rien sur le dialecte des Moluques. Mais comme <persName ref="tsraffles">Raffles</persName> le nomme <hi rend="underline">Malay</hi>,
                    je suppose qu’il ne diffère pas autant que le Javanois du Malay de Malacca.“</p>
            <p>Of Amboyna &amp; the other spice islands I know little beyond what is contained
                    in the celebrated works of <persName ref="fvalentijn">Valentyn</persName> &amp;
                        <persName ref="gerumpf">Rumphius</persName>. In common with all others of
                    the archipelago they have each their language of the interior, being a dialect
                    of the Polynesian; &amp; besides this, the Malayan, as a general medium of
                    communication, ist spoken in the sea-ports &amp; generally along the coasts. It
                        <add>(the Malayan)</add> was in itself, originally, a Polynesian dialect,
                    but has been so changed by various admixtures as to become a distinct language –
                    written in a modified Arabic character &amp; essentially connected with the
                    Mahometan religion. The <persName ref="cbrosses">President De Brosses</persName>
                    first employed the term of „Polynesia“ as a geographical distinction, &amp; I
                    availed myself of its adjective, „Polynesian“, to denote that extraordinary
                    chain of language found to extend from the island of Madagascar to the further
                    limit of the Pacific ocean – excepting always the languages of New Holland, New
                    Guinea, &amp; many smaler islands inhabited by Negritos.</p>
            <p>5.° „Quelle es tvotre opinion sur la priorité des Moluques <pb n="178v"/> pour
                    les rapports avec l’Inde? J’avoue que j’ai cru au contraire la civilisation de
                    <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName> antérieure à toute autre dans ces mers. Un passage de l’<bibl sameAs="351">Histoire de Java</bibl> de <persName ref="tsraffles">Raffles</persName>
                    vient à l’appui de cette hypothèse. Une tradition Javanoise rapportée <bibl sameAs="351">vol. II.
                    p. 84.</bibl> raconte que <hi rend="underline">Aru</hi> <hi rend="underline">Bandan</hi>, venant des Moluques, connessoit moins bien que <hi rend="underline">Sawéla</hi> <hi rend="underline">Chala</hi> les
                    caractères et l’écriture d’<hi rend="underline">Aji</hi> <hi rend="underline">Saka</hi>. Or, ces caractères étoient sans doute Indien. Ce
                    n’est là qu’une conte, mais les contes de ce genre renferment quelques fois des
                    traits de verité cachés dans des recits fabuleux.“</p>
            <p>My opinion agrees with yours, Monsieur, that the island of <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName> (with that of <placeName ref="Bali">
                  <hi rend="underline">Balli</hi>
               </placeName> in its immediate vicinity) was the <hi rend="underline">earliest</hi>, as it has certainly been the <hi rend="underline">principal</hi> seat of Hindu (Buddhist) colonisation; &amp;
                    I am not aware of any grounds for believing that the Moluccas have any sort of
                    claim to priority in this or any othe respect – excepting their rich vegetable
                    produce. Nor indeed does my excellent friend <persName ref="tsraffles">Raffles</persName> (who made Javanese more than Malayan literature the
                    object of his attention) express himself very decidedly on the subject when he
                    says: „The Javanese annals do not trace the first coming of the people from
                    Western India much beyond the thousand years back, but <hi rend="underline">tradition justifies us in believing</hi> that long before <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName> was
                    civilised, the inhabitants of the more Eastern islands, &amp; particularly the
                    Moluccas, had considerably <hi rend="underline">emerged from a state of
                        barbarism</hi>. This tradition is strongly confirmed by the <hi rend="underline">probability</hi> &amp;c.“</p>
            <p>6.° „Le mot <hi rend="underline">Aji</hi>, prince, ne peut-il pas venir d’<hi rend="underline">ajong</hi>, mettre en ordre, arranger?“ &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="179r"/> As the word <hi rend="underline">aji</hi> belongs to the High
                    language of <placeName ref="Java">Java</placeName> (quite distinct from the ordinary dialects) we must look for
                    its meaning in the Sanskrit, where it signifies „victorious“, rather than in the
                    Malayan; nor can it be admitted that the word <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831_05_21/g1.png"/> <hi rend="underline">aji</hi>
                    has such an affinity to <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831_05_21/g2.png"/> or <graphic url="Marsden/Marsden-WvH_1831_05_21/g3.png"/> <hi rend="underline">ajōng</hi> as to warrant
                    an etymological inference.</p>
            <p>In these answers I hope I have explained myself with sufficient clearness. Should
                    it prove otherwise, I shall be happy to afford any further light you may
                    require, &amp;</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with apologies for the delay that has occured, I have the honour to be,
                        with the highest respect, <lb/>My dear Sir, <lb/>Your faithful &amp;
                        obedient <lb/>servant</salute>
               <signed>W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Marsden</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency
                    <lb/>the Baron de Humboldt
                    <lb/>&amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</addrLine>
               </address>
               <lb/>
               <pb n="179v vacat"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
