<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- IN BEARBEITUNG von FZ -->
<?xml-model href="../WvH_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de"
     telota:doctype="wvh_letters">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joseph John Freeman an Wilhelm von Humboldt, 02.12.1831<idno type="BBAW">309</idno>
            </title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/135657458">Frank Zimmer</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/120492644">Jürgen Trabant</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/1053159110">Ute Tintemann</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6587-3353">Lou Klappenbach</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7447-4589">Sascha Grabsch</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Elise Hanrahan</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <title>Wilhelm von Humboldt: Online-Edition der sprachwissenschaftlichen Korrespondenz</title>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de">
                    Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften (BBAW)
                </ref>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="orig">Grundlage der Edition: Berlin, SBBPK, Coll. ling. fol. 153, acc. 11070, Bl.
                            129–131</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="print"/>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="KMV">S. 345</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="Mattson"> 12386</bibl>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
            <listPerson type="mentioned">
               <person corresp="ccolville">
                  <persName>Colville, Sir Charles</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="jcrawfurd">
                  <persName>Crawfurd, John</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="rdrury">
                  <persName>Drury, Robert</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="eflacourt">
                  <persName>Flacourt, Ètienne de</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listBibl type="mentioned">
               <bibl corresp="101">Crawfurd, John: History of the Indian Archipelago: Containing an
                    account of the manners, arts, languages, religions, institutions, and commerce
                    of its inhabitants, 3 Bände (Edinburgh: A. Constable and Co. 1820)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="920">Drury, Robert: Madagascar: or, Robert Drury’s Journal during
                    fifteen years captivity on that island (London 1729)</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="914">Flacourt, Étienne de: Dictionnaire de la langue de Madagascar avec
                    un petit recueil de noms &amp; dictions propres des choses qui sont d’une mesme
                    espèce. Plus quelques mot du langage des sauvages de la baye de Saldagne au Cap
                    de Bonne Espérance. Un petit catéchisme &amp; des prières du matin &amp; du soir
                    que les missionaires font &amp; enseignent aux néophytes &amp; catéchumènes de
                    cette isle, le tout en françois &amp; en cette langue (Paris 1658)</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <ab type="incipit">My dear Sir, I must throw myself on your
                        kindness to forgive me for having so long delayed replying to your most
                        obliging and valuable communication …</ab>
         </abstract>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName key="jjfreeman">Freeman, Joseph John</persName>
               <date type="author" when="1831-12-02"/>
               <placeName key="Antananarivo">Tananarivo</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName key="wvh">Humboldt, Wilhelm von</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <ref target="311" type="prev">September 1830</ref>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote scribe="jjfreeman">Eigenhändig</handNote>
         </handNotes>
         <langUsage n="paz">
            <language ident="mg">Malagasy (Madegassisch)</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <list>
            <item n="name">FZ</item>
            <item n="date">12. Februar 2015</item>
            <item n="status">in Bearbeitung</item>
         </list>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <pb n="129r"/>
               <dateline>Tananarivo, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Dec
                        1831</dateline>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To Baron Will.<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> <sic>Humbolt</sic>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>&amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I must throw myself<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Zu dem englischen
                    Missionar Joseph John Freeman (1774–1851) siehe Gerald H. Anderson (1998): <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</hi>, New
                        York: Macmillan, S. 225. [FZ]</note> on your kindness to forgive me for
                    having so long delayed replying to your most obliging and valuable communication
                    of ____.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Lücke im Manuskript.</note> The fact
                    is I had left <placeName ref="Mauritius">Mauritius</placeName> when your letter
                    arrived there. I was spending some time at the Cape of Good Hope. <hi rend="underline">There</hi>, through the obliging care of His Excellency
                        <persName ref="ccolville">Sir Charles Colville</persName>, I received your
                    communication, but of course some delay had been occasioned by having to forward
                    the letter from <placeName ref="Mauritius">Mauritius</placeName> to the Cape.
                    And, at the moment of its coming to hand, I was busily engaged in preparing for
                    my return to Madagascar, and could not command sufficient time to do myself the
                    pleasure of acknowledging the receipt of your favor. I resolved on occupying
                    part of my time during the voyage, in replying at length to your highly useful
                    and interesting suggestions and inquiries respecting the Malagasy language, –
                    and I confess I felt most deeply mortified, when on examining one day in my
                    cabin, my Letter Box, I found I had left your letter at the Cape. On reaching
                    Tamatave I sent back immediately to my friend in <placeName ref="Kapstadt">Cape
                        Town</placeName>, under whose charge I left my letters &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>, requesting him to forward your communication to
                    me, without delay. I have no doubt it is now on its way, – and instantly it
                    comes to hand, I shall consider it one of my first duties, to give you as full
                    as explanation as I can of the various points you have suggested. I feel <pb n="129v"/> almost ashamed to intrude on your attention with so
                        <sic>lenthened</sic> an apology and explanation, but that I am anxious to
                    exonerate myself from the charge or even the appearance of neglect, – and I will
                    only add, that making arrangements for my family’s return to Europe while I
                        <add>might</add> spend a couple of years or so again in Madagascar, – and
                    preparing to bring with me to this vast country, an immense supply seeds, plants
                        &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>, horses, merino sheep &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> really absorbed
                    all my time &amp; attention.</p>
            <p>Should your letter reach me before I have an opportunity to forward this, I
                    purpose entering on the various critical inquiries you have made. Should it not
                    come to hand so soon, I must be content to remark on one or two of them as they
                    occur to my memory.</p>
            <p>And first with regard to the term for God. <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriamanitra</foreign> is the general expression used by the natives, in
                    this the interior of the Country. On the coast <foreign sameAs="mg">Zanahary</foreign> is more common, or as I have somewhere seen it spelt
                        <foreign sameAs="mg">Zanhar</foreign>. I think in <bibl sameAs="914">Flacourt</bibl>. The Malagasy very frequently combine the two names
                        “<foreign sameAs="mg">Andriamanitra Andriananahary</foreign>.” They do not
                    appear to possess any definite ideas respecting the origin or the form of these
                    different names. <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriana</foreign>, signifies as you
                    justly suppose Sovereign, Prince, Nobleman, – and hence in speaking of the
                    reigning Sovereign, the usual expression is <foreign sameAs="mg">Nag
                        Andriana</foreign> – says so &amp; so – does so &amp; so. The final <hi rend="underline">a</hi> has been added merely in accordance with the general
                    analogy of the language. It is not sounded, and for my own part I should prefer
                    to omit it. And the first letter is usually sounded very softly. – The word
                    might almost be spelt <foreign sameAs="mg">‘ndrīan</foreign> (sounding the i
                    as in French,/ and you would have the native sound. It is no doubt the same word
                    that <bibl sameAs="920">Drury</bibl> gives “Dean” as used by the natives in the
                    southwest, as copied by <sic>
                  <persName ref="jcrawfurd">Crawford</persName>
               </sic>
                    in <bibl sameAs="101">his Vocabulary</bibl>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Gemeint sind damit die Wortlisten im <bibl sameAs="101">2. Band der <hi rend="italic">History of the Indian Archipelago</hi>
                  </bibl>, S.
                        125–192.</note>. “<foreign sameAs="mg">Andriambaventy</foreign>” signifies
                        <pb n="130r"/> “a great noble”, – or “nobleman” and is always here applied
                    to the Judges. The <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">baventy</hi>
               </foreign> you will recognise as the <foreign sameAs="mg">Vaventy </foreign> of the Malagasy, signifying great; – V, changed into B
                    in composition after M and N changed into that M first gratiâ euphoniae. In some Provinces <foreign sameAs="mg">Maventy</foreign> is used for <foreign sameAs="mg">Vaventy</foreign>.
                        <foreign sameAs="mg">Venty</foreign> also signifies large, full; – e. g.
                        <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">Vary iray venty</hi>
               </foreign>
                    one large Rice, – i. e. one full grain – being the smallest amount known in the
                    names of the Malagasy money equal to the 720.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> part
                    of a Dollar. <foreign sameAs="mg">Venty</foreign> means also a Unit, and is at
                    times used in that sense. <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">Manitra</hi>
               </foreign> (to return from the digression/ signifies sweet
                    – that is, to the <hi rend="underline">Smell</hi>, for to the <hi rend="underline">Taste</hi> <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">mamy</hi>
               </foreign> is used, as “<foreign sameAs="mg">sira
                        mamy</foreign>,” sugar, that is salt sweet – sweet salt. Now, here is only
                    the word <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">manitra</hi>
               </foreign> is
                    applied to God, being appended to <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">Andriana</hi>
               </foreign>, (na lost in composition/ is it difficult to
                    divine. The Natives cannot explain it. Etymology they are yet not familiar with,
                    &amp; they have not any custom that explains the use of the word in this
                    particular connexion. <foreign sameAs="mg">Lanitra</foreign> is <hi rend="underline">heaven</hi> – the <foreign sameAs="mg">Langhitz</foreign>
                    of some authors – (n – is pronounced ng on the coast – ן of the Hebrews – &amp;
                    tra final is usually sounded tz by the Sakalaves and other people near the Sea;/
                    but then the analogy of the language would certainly require <foreign sameAs="mg">
                  <hi rend="underline">Danitra</hi> Andriandanitra </foreign> –
                    as <foreign sameAs="mg">Andrian-dahy</foreign> – when the l of <foreign sameAs="mg">lahy</foreign> (male/ is changed into d./ This word of course
                    means a Noble<hi rend="underline">man</hi> in distinction from <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriam-bavy</foreign> (<foreign sameAs="mg">vavy</foreign>
                    female) a Noblewoman. If <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriamanitra</foreign>
                    signifies Sovereign of Heaven it is a formation of the word quite unique in the
                    language and is a glaring exception to <subst>
                  <del>an
                            universal</del>
                  <add>a</add>
               </subst> rule, otherwise universal. As
                    the word stands, it means rather The Sovereign sweet – or scented. Possibly
                    there may have been originally some incense some ceremony of using Sweet incense
                    in the appointment of their Kings; – and the word then used <pb n="130v"/> might
                    refer to this, – and have been retained in the language to the present time,
                    tho’ its reason, &amp; the custom, have been lost by the lapse of time. There
                    exists still some custom of anointing the Sovereign on succeeding to the throne,
                    – and I rather think, that it is the particular act of anointing that confers
                    the public right to the crown – or rather, <hi rend="underline">recognition</hi>
                    of that right of the party claiming the <unclear>Empire</unclear>, – and
                    corresponding in some degree with our public coronation in Europe. (By the way,
                    crowns have been hitherto unknown in this country. I believe I have the honor of
                    introducing the first. I brought one with me on my return from the Cape – &amp;
                    which now in the possession of the Queen, Ranavalona.)</p>
            <p>Although <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriana</foreign> is the common expression for
                    the Sovereign, <foreign sameAs="mg">Mpanjaka</foreign> is also in very
                    frequent use. It is the noun, or participle of the verb <foreign sameAs="mg">Manjaka</foreign>. <foreign sameAs="mg">Jaka</foreign> is the root – and
                    is pronounced Dzaka – it signifies to be able or competent to do a thing; – as
                    in speaking of a person unable to lift a certain weight – or to carry a load,
                    that is found too heavy for him, the familiar expression would be “<foreign sameAs="mg">Tsy jaka izy</foreign>” – “not able he” – i. e. he cannot – he
                    is not equal to it. <foreign sameAs="mg">Man</foreign> – is evidently the
                    formation of numerous verbs and is derived from <foreign sameAs="mg">Manao</foreign> to do or act, and here as in many other cases, it seems to
                    take simply the form of <hi rend="underline">to be</hi> – “to be able” – “to be
                    competent” – “one who can manage” – “can effect” – “can do” – &amp; therefore
                    having power, authority &amp;.<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> as a Sovereign.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign sameAs="mg">Andriananahary</foreign> &amp; <foreign sameAs="mg">Zanahary</foreign> I regard as radically the same. <foreign sameAs="mg">Hary</foreign> is the root – signifying possessions – propriety – wealth –
                    and may here refer to the Universal proprietorship vested in the Deity, as Lord
                    &amp; owner of the Universe – or as the Natives express the idea “<foreign sameAs="mg">Tompo ny lanitra sy ny tany</foreign>” – “<foreign sameAs="mg">Tompo ny izao tontolo izan</foreign>” – “Lord of this all
                    this.”</p>
            <p>Why it is <foreign sameAs="mg">Andria<hi rend="underline">n</hi>anahary</foreign> instead of <foreign sameAs="mg">Andria<hi rend="underline">z</hi>anahary</foreign> I know not – but I think the
                    genius of the language prefers the sound of N generally and especially in
                    composition (<foreign sameAs="mg">Neny</foreign> is common for <foreign sameAs="mg">Reny</foreign> a mother) <foreign sameAs="mg">Maniana</foreign> signifies <hi rend="underline">to have</hi>. <foreign sameAs="mg">Zana</foreign> – may be for <foreign sameAs="mg">Zanaka</foreign> a Son – final k is often lost – always in <foreign sameAs="mg">Zana’ny</foreign> his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="131r"/> On the subject of publishing any Grammar or Dictionary in this
                    language, I have no <sic>expectation</sic> I have no <sic>expectation</sic> that
                    anything of the kind will be effected here, or by <orgName ref="16">our Society
                        in London</orgName>, at present. We possess abundance of materials – our
                    collections of words – phrases – &amp; native expressions,
                        <unclear>Kabars</unclear> – &amp; compositions of all kind are immense, –
                    but we could neither command sufficient time to arrange them for a respectable
                    publication, – nor are we assured that the expenses incurred would be at all
                    indemnified in any quarter, because there <supplied cert="high">are</supplied>
                    so few who would feel much interest in the undertaking.</p>
            <p>I should delight to see something of the kind from your pen. You have gained a
                    highly respectable acquaintance with the language in its leading characters
                    &amp; any work you might publish would form a valuable guide to any further
                    publications or illustrations on the same subject, more especially if your
                    comprehensive acquaintance with other Oriental Languages were made to bear on
                    the history &amp; illustration of this.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to remain <lb/>My Dear Sir <lb/>Your very faithful
                        <lb/>&amp; obliged Servant</salute>
               <signed>J. J. Freeman</signed>
               <lb/>
               <pb n="131v vacat"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
