<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../WvH_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de"
     telota:doctype="wvh_letters">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Young an Wilhelm von Humboldt, vor August 1827<idno type="BBAW">759</idno>
            </title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/135657458">Frank Zimmer</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/120492644">Jürgen Trabant</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/1053159110">Ute Tintemann</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6587-3353">Lou Klappenbach</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7447-4589">Sascha Grabsch</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Elise Hanrahan</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <title>Wilhelm von Humboldt: Online-Edition der sprachwissenschaftlichen
                  Korrespondenz</title>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de"> Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften
                  (BBAW) </ref>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative Commons
                  Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="orig">Verbleib unbekannt</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="print">Grundlage der Edition: Young 1827, S. 92–100; Young 1855, S.
                     433–441</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="KMV"/>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="Mattson">Mattson 12010</bibl>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
            <listPerson type="mentioned">
               <person corresp="jpabel">
                  <persName>Abel-Rémusat, Jean-Pierre</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="apollonius">
                  <persName>Apollonios Dyskolos (Grammatiker)</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="wblackstone">
                  <persName>Blackstone, Sir William</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="jburton">
                  <persName>Burton, James</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="wcobbett">
                  <persName>Cobbett, William</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="georgkve">
                  <persName>Georg IV., König von England</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="avh">
                  <persName>Humboldt, Alexander von</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="jmilton">
                  <persName>Milton, John</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="muhammadali">
                  <persName>Muhammad Ali Pascha</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="htattam">
                  <persName>Tattam, Henry</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="jhtooke">
                  <persName>Tooke, John Horne</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listBibl type="mentioned">
               <bibl corresp="1355">Burton, James (1825–1829): Excerpta hieroglyphica: or exact
                  copies of various hieroglyphical inscriptions and sculptured monuments still
                  existing in Egypt and Nubia, and at Mount Sinai, Kairo: Privatdruck</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="1356">Cobbett, William (1818): A Grammar of the English Language, in a
                  Series of Letters. Intended for the Use of Schools and of Young Persons in
                  General; But, More Especially for the Use of Soldiers, Sailors, Apprentices, and
                  Plough-Boys, New York: Printed for the author by Clayton and Kingsland</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="202">Humboldt, Wilhelm von (1827): Lettre à Monsieur Abel Rémusat, sur
                  la nature des formes grammaticales en général, et sur le génie de la langue
                  Chinoise en particulier, Paris: Dondey-Dupré</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="701">Tattam, Henry (1830): A compendious Grammar of the Egyptian
                  language as contained in the Coptic and Sahidic dialects; with observations on the
                  Bashmuric: together with alphabets and numerals in the Hieroglyphic and Enchorial
                  characters; and a few explanTattamatory observations: by the Rev. Henry Tattam,
                  M.A. F.R.S.L. &amp;c. &amp;c. Rector of St. Cuthbert’s, Bedford. With an Appendix,
                  consisting of the Rudiments of a Dictionary of the Ancient Egyptian language in
                  the Enchorial character: by Thomas Young, M.D. F.R.S. H.M.R.S.L. Foreign associate
                  of the Royal Institute of Paris, London: Arch</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="1357">Tooke, John Horne (1786): Ἐπεα πτεροεντα. Or, the Diversions of
                  Purley, London: J. Johnson [Erstausgabe]</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <ab type="incipit">My dear Sir, I am happy to tell you that our prospects of new
               documents from Egypt …</ab>
         </abstract>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName key="tyoung">Young, Thomas</persName>
               <date type="editor" when="1827-07-31"/>
               <placeName key="Ohne Ort">ohne Ort</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName key="wvh">Humboldt, Wilhelm von</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <langUsage n="">
            <language ident="Egyd">Ägyptisch (Demotisch)</language>
            <language ident="Egyp">Ägyptische Hieroglyphen</language>
            <language ident="zh">Chinesisch</language>
            <language ident="de">Deutsch</language>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
            <language ident="cop">Koptisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <list>
            <item n="name">FZ</item>
            <item n="date">15. Juni 2020</item>
            <item n="status">in Bearbeitung</item>
         </list>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I AM happy to tell you that our prospects of new documents from Egypt are very
               rapidly increasing: <persName ref="jburton">Mr. Burton</persName> has had the good
               fortune to discover at length, in a mosque, the triple inscription for which he has
               been some years in search; and he has been negotiating with the <persName ref="muhammadali">Pacha</persName> for its removal. From its magnitude and state
               of preservation, there is every reason to believe that it will rival the pillar of
               Rosetta in its importance; and I sincerely hope that it will tend to check the
               wildness of conjecture, which has been rioting without bounds in the regions of
               Egyptian literature. <persName ref="htattam">Mr. Tattam</persName> is printing <bibl sameAs="701">a Coptic grammar</bibl>, and I am preparing an Appendix, which is to
               contain the rudiments of an Enchorial Lexicon: I ardently wish that <persName ref="jburton">Mr. Burton</persName>’s <bibl sameAs="1355">inscriptions</bibl> may
               come to my assistance before I complete it. I have received nothing from France or
               from Germany for these four years past: even what is published seems by some fatality
               to have been withheld from me; and the booksellers send no answers to my commissions.
               I trust <persName ref="avh">your brother</persName> will not forget his kind promise
               to think of me at <placeName ref="Berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
            <p>I have to thank him and you for your obliging present of your <bibl sameAs="202">
                  <hi rend="italic">Letter to Abel Remusat on the Genius of the Chinese
                  Language</hi>
               </bibl>, which has greatly interested me: the best return that I can
               make will be to give you some remarks which have occurred to me on the language of
               hieroglyphics in general, and on the character of the English language, which seems
               to approach, in its simplicity, as you have yourself observed, to the natural
               structure of the oldest languages, immediately related to the hieroglyphical form of
               representation. I fear, however, that I must apologize to you for the want of method
               with which I shall be obliged at present to throw my fragments together: but it may
               be allowable to make some difference between a letter and a finished essay. </p>
            <p>Hieroglyphics, in their primitive form, are scarcely to be considered in any case as
               simply a mode of expressing an oral language: they may be a direct and independent
               representation of our thoughts, that is, of recollections, or sentiments, or
               intentions, collateral to the representation of the same thoughts by the language of
               sounds. We find, in many of the Egyptian monuments, a double expression of the same
               sense: first, a simple picture, for instance, of a votary presenting a vase to a
               sitting deity; each characterized by some peculiarity of form, and each distinguished
               also by a name written over him; and this may be called a pure hieroglyphical
               representation, though it scarcely amounts to a language, any more than the look of
               love is the language of a lover. But we universally find that the tablet is
               accompanied by a greater variety of characters which certainly do constitute a
               language, although we know little or nothing of the sounds of that language; but its
               import is, that "such a king offers a vase to the deity;" and on the other side, that
               "the deity grants to the king health and strength, and beauty and riches, and
               dominion and power." It is common to see, in these inscriptions, a number of
               characters introduced, which are evidently identical with some of those in the
               tablets: and however some of them may occasionally have been employed phonetically,
               there can be no question of the nature of the changes which their employment must
               have gone through before they assumed the character of sounds: but this is altogether
               a separate consideration, and foreign to the present purpose. </p>
            <p>Now it is obvious that objects, delineated with the intention of representing the
               originals to the eye by their form, must necessarily be nouns substantive; and that
               the picture, containing no verb whatever, can scarcely be said to constitute either a
               positive or a negative assertion. At the same time, it I must be allowed that a
               picture of <persName ref="georgkve">King George the Fourth</persName>’s coronation,
               with the date 19 July, 1821, could scarcely be considered otherwise than as asserting
               a historical truth; and if any emblem of Truth were attached to it, or if it were
               deposited among the records of other historical facts, it would be equivalent to the
               expression, <persName ref="georgkve">"George IV.</persName> crowned in July, 1821,"
               which <hi rend="italic">scarcely</hi> wants the verb <hi rend="italic">was</hi> to
               convert it into a positive assertion of a fact. </p>
            <p>Strictly speaking, however, there seems to be no direct mode of supplying the want of
               the verb <hi rend="italic">is</hi> or <hi rend="italic">was</hi> in pure
               hieroglyphical writing; and if any such sign was employed in the Egyptian or the old
               Chinese hieroglyphics, its introduction must have been arbitrary or conventional;
               like the employment of a postulate in mathematics. Every other part of a language
               appears capable of being reduced, with more or less circumlocution, to the form of a
               noun substantive; and the English language appears to approach to the Chinese in the
               facility with which all the forms of grammar may be shaken off. </p>
            <p>There is, however, often occasion, in such cases, for a certain degree of metaphor
               approaching to poetical latitude; and hence it may happen that the least literary
               nations are sometimes the most poetical. It is, in fact, impossible to exclude
               metaphor altogether from the most prosaic language; and it is frequently difficult to
               say where metaphor ends and strict logical prose begins; but by degrees the metaphor
               drops, and the simple figurative sense is retained. Thus we may say <hi rend="italic">liquid ruby</hi> with the same exact meaning as <hi rend="italic">crimson
                  wine</hi>; and yet <hi rend="italic">ruby</hi> would never be called an adjective,
               though employed merely to express the colour: in <hi rend="italic">coral lips</hi>,
               however, the <hi rend="italic">coral</hi>, first used metaphorically, is converted by
               habit into an adjective, and the expression is considered as synonymous with <hi rend="italic">labri corallini</hi>. </p>
            <p>The general custom in English is to place the figurative substantive, used as an
               adjective by comparison, or by abstraction, before the name which retains its proper
               sense: thus a chesnut horse is a chesnut like or chesnut coloured horse; a horse
               chesnut is a coarse kind of chesnut: and in this manner we are enabled to use almost
               every English noun substantive as an adjective, by an ellipsis of the word <hi rend="italic">like</hi>, which, if inserted entire or abridged, would make a real
               adjective of the word, as war<hi rend="italic">like</hi>, friend<hi rend="italic">ly</hi>. But this omission of the termination, like other figures of speech, is
               easily forgotten in the ordinary forms of language; and the Germans, as well as the
               English, make use of almost all their substantives in the place of adjectives, though
               they are more in the habit of continuing them into single long words. When, however,
               the substantives are so used, they generally become by abstraction real adjectives:
               for we seldom think of a <hi rend="italic">chesnut</hi>, in speaking of the colour of
               a horse; but the idea of a light brown coat, with an ugly pale-red mane and tail, and
               a fidgety temper, is very likely to occur to us: and in a horse chesnut the idea of a
               horse is out of the question; we only think of a coarse fruit which a man cannot eat:
               so that the true sense, in both these instances, is that of a quality; but <hi rend="italic">coral lips</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ivory hands</hi> are rather
               elliptical expressions, composed of two substantives, which might fairly be
               represented hieroglyphically by the assistance of a branch of coral and an elephant’s
               tusk. But to describe an abstract quality by any hieroglyphic character,
               representative of form only, would be generally impossible: colours might be
               imitated, if we supposed coloured figures to be employed; but other simple ideas,
               such as those of sound or touch, could never be immediately presented to the eye; and
               some circuitous invention would always be required for their representation. </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="jhtooke">Horne Tooke</persName> has shewn,<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Gemeint ist wohl Horne Tookes <bibl sameAs="1357">Ἐπεα πτεροεντα. <hi rend="italic">Or, the Diversions of
               Purley</hi>
                  </bibl>, zuerst erschienen in <placeName ref="London">London</placeName> im Jahr 1786. [FZ]</note> with considerable felicity
               of illustration, that all the parts of speech may be resolved into the noun and the
               verb; but he has not pointed out so clearly that every verb may be resolved into a
               noun and the single primitive verb is or was, which, in this sense, may be said to be
               the only essential verb in any language; as we find, indeed, in the Coptic, that
               almost every noun becomes a verb, either by the addition of PE, or sometimes even
               without it. Thus, <hi rend="italic">the morning</hi> BLUSHES is synonymous with <hi rend="italic">the morning</hi> IS <hi rend="italic">red</hi>; <hi rend="italic">he
                  loves justice</hi>, with <hi rend="italic">he</hi> IS <hi rend="italic">a lover of
                  justice</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> AM <hi rend="italic">an
               Englishman</hi>, with the <hi rend="italic">person now speaking</hi> IS <hi rend="italic">an Englishman</hi>. But this must be understood of is, was, or will
               be, in all its tenses; the idea of time, if expressed, being an essential part of the
               verbal sense. </p>
            <p>I confess that some of these reflections have occurred to me in looking over a very
               singular work, which I had the curiosity to take up, in order to see what kind of
               information could be possessed by a person notoriously and professedly ignorant of
               the origin and relations of the language which he attempts to teach; and, in short,
               what kind of light could be diffused by an apostle of darkness. Blunders, and some of
               them ridiculous enough, must, of course, be found in the works of such a person, but
               most of them are such as every schoolboy might correct; and there really is so much
               of sagacity in some of <persName ref="wcobbett">Mr. Cobbett</persName>’s remarks on
               the errors of others, that they well deserve the attention of such as are ambitious
               to write or speak with perfect accuracy. </p>
            <p>I shall not attempt to enter into a regular criticism of <bibl sameAs="1356">this <hi rend="italic">Grammar</hi>
               </bibl>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Siehe zu
                  Cobbett und seinen Sprachstudien: F. Aarts (1994): William Cobbett’s Grammar of
                  the English Language. In: <hi rend="italic">Neuphilologische Mitteilungen</hi> 95,
                  Nr. 3, S. 319–332. [FZ]</note>; I shall merely make a few miscellaneous
               observations, as they have occurred to me in reading it, several of which would be
               equally applicable to the best of the existing works of a similar nature. </p>
            <p>In <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter III.</bibl> we are told that <hi rend="italic">long and
                  short</hi>, though adjectives, do not express <hi rend="italic">qualities</hi>,
               but merely dimension or duration; from a singular misconception of the proper sense
               of the word <hi rend="italic">quality</hi>. We find, in <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter
                  IV.</bibl>, the rule given by most grammarians, though not by all, that the
               article A becomes AN, when it is followed by any word beginning with a vowel; but it
               is surely more natural to follow the sound than the spelling, and, as we should never
               think of saying an <hi rend="italic">youthful</hi> bride, it seems equally incorrect
               to say an <hi rend="italic">useful</hi> piece of furniture; for the initial sound is
               precisely the same. In the same manner A <hi rend="italic">unit</hi> and A <hi rend="italic">European</hi>, seems to sound more agreeable than AN; and the best
               speakers appear to adopt this custom. </p>
            <p>
               <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter VIII.</bibl> gives us a rule for doubling the last letter
               of a verb in the participle if an accent is on the last syllable; but it should be
               observed that the L is doubled, whether accented or not, as in <hi rend="italic">caballing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">travelled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">levelled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cavilled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">controlled</hi>.
               The same letter contains a "List of verbs, which, by some persons, are erroneously
               deemed irregular,"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 60. [FZ]</note>
               and which have been so deemed from the time of our German and Saxon ancestors, though
                  <persName ref="wcobbett">Mr. Cobbett</persName> thinks it would be more
               philosophical to conjugate them regularly. Thus we may see at once that <hi rend="italic">freeze</hi> may as well give us <hi rend="italic">frozen</hi>, as
                  <hi rend="italic">frieren</hi> gives the Germans <hi rend="italic">gefroren</hi>;
               that <hi rend="italic">hang</hi> may make <hi rend="italic">hung</hi> or <hi rend="italic">hanged</hi>, according to its sense, as in German we have <hi rend="italic">hienge</hi> from <hi rend="italic">hangen</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">hängte</hi> from <hi rend="italic">hängen</hi>, to execute. For <hi rend="italic">sling</hi> and <hi rend="italic">slung</hi>, we have authority in
                  <hi rend="italic">schlingen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">geschlungen</hi>, for <hi rend="italic">spring</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sprung</hi> in <hi rend="italic">springen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gesprungen</hi>; for <hi rend="italic">swollen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">swam</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">swum</hi>, and
                  <hi rend="italic">swung</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">geschwollen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">geschwommen</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">geschwungen</hi>. And it is
               quite clear from these examples that "the bad practice of abbreviating, or
               shortening," has nothing to do with the matter. </p>
            <p>In <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter XIV.</bibl> we have a very distinct examination of a
               rule in punctuation which has been commonly adopted by good printers, without so
               distinct a description of its foundation. "Commas are made use of, when phrases, that
               is to say, 'portions' of words, are 'throw<hi rend="italic">ed</hi>' into a sentence,
               and which are not absolutely necessary to assist in its grammatical
                  construction."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 78. [FZ]</note>
               In a word, two commas are very nearly equivalent to the old fashioned parenthesis.
               Again, "the apostrophe ought to be called the mark not of elision, but of <hi rend="italic">laziness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vulgarity</hi>;"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 81. [FZ]</note> a remark made in
               truly classical taste, which might have been extended with perfect propriety to the
               subject of the next paragraph, the <hi rend="italic">Hyphen</hi>, the insertion of
               which is, to make it uncertain whether the words united by it are one word or two. He
               goes on admirably in the next page. "<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, like parentheses,
               are <hi rend="italic">interrupters</hi>, and much more troublesome interrupters,
               because they generally tell a much longer story. The employing of them arises, in
               almost all cases, from confusion in the mind of the writer. He finds the matter <hi rend="italic">too much for him</hi>. He has not the talent to work it all up into
               one lucid whole; and, therefore, he puts part of it into <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 83. [FZ]</note>
               ..... "Instead of the word <hi rend="italic">and</hi>, you often see people put <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi>. For what reason I should like to know. But to this <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> is sometimes added a <hi rend="italic">c</hi>; thus, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>. <hi rend="italic">And</hi> is, in Latin, <hi rend="italic">et</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is the first letter of the
               Latin word <hi rend="italic">caetera</hi>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Bei
                  Horne 1818, S. 83 steht korrekt: <hi rend="italic">cetera</hi>. [FZ]</note>, which
               means <hi rend="italic">the like</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">so on</hi>. This
               abbreviation of a foreign word is a most convenient thing for such writers as have
               too much indolence or too little sense to say fully and clearly what they ought to
               say. If you <hi rend="italic">mean</hi> to say and the like, or, <hi rend="italic">and so on</hi>, why not say it? ... The abbreviation is very frequently made use
               of <hi rend="italic">without the writer having</hi> any idea of its import."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 83f. [FZ]</note> But it is surely a
               mischievous maxim, never to "think of <hi rend="italic">mending</hi> what you write.
               Let it <hi rend="italic">go</hi>. No patching; no <hi rend="italic">after
                  painting</hi>."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 85. [FZ]</note>
               On the other hand he is right in protesting "against the use of what, by some, is
               called the <hi rend="italic">dash</hi>. Who is to know what is intended by the use of
               these <hi rend="italic">dashes?</hi> .... It is a cover for ignorance as to the use
               of points; and it can answer no other purpose."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 85. [FZ]</note>
            </p>
            <p>In <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter XV.</bibl> there is a singular conceit with regard to
               the keeping up a distinction between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">an</hi>, where it is insisted that we must not say "<hi rend="italic">a</hi> dog,
               cat, owl, and sparrow," because owl requires <hi rend="italic">an</hi>; "and that it
               should be a dog, a cat, an owl, and a sparrow;"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 87. [FZ]</note> which is certainly better, and would be so, even
               if there were no owl in the question. </p>
            <p>
               <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter XVII.</bibl> The criticism on <persName ref="jmilton">Milton</persName>’s "than <hi rend="italic">whom</hi> none higher sat,"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 106. [FZ]</note> is perfectly
               correct. <hi rend="italic">Than</hi> is never a preposition, and is simply a
               variation from the older <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, both in English and in German.
                  <hi rend="italic">John is better than James</hi> means simply John is good first,
               then James: <hi rend="italic">er</hi> is <hi rend="italic">eher</hi> or <hi rend="italic">e’er</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Who</hi> would sound awkwardly, but
               would be more grammatical. </p>
            <p>
               <bibl sameAs="1356">Letter XIX.</bibl> gives a definition of the ellipsis, which
               would be a lesson to <persName ref="apollonius">Apollonius</persName> himself: the
               compasses, it seems, "do not take their sweep all round, but leave out parts of the
               area or surface." The objection to <persName ref="wblackstone">Blackstone</persName>’s language is very questionable. "The very <hi rend="italic">scheme and model</hi> WAS settled,"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne
                  1818, S. 123. [FZ]</note> may, perhaps, be defended, because scheme and model are
               considered as one thing, the words being intended to illustrate each other, but not
               to point out different attributes of the administration of justice; and both words
               may be admitted, as a collective term, to govern a singular rather than a plural
               verb. It seems also to be an error to make <hi rend="italic">with</hi> a conjunction
               rather than a preposition, and to say, "The bag, with the guineas and dollars in it,
                  <hi rend="italic">were</hi> stolen,"<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne
                  1818, S. 129. [FZ]</note> or "zeal, with discretion, <hi rend="italic">do</hi>
                  much."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 129. [FZ]</note> "I
               expected to have seen," is justly noticed as a common error for "I expected to
                  see."<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Horne 1818, S. 136. [FZ]</note> The
               meaning of an active verb is erroneously confounded with that of a <hi rend="italic">transitive</hi> verb, in the remarks on the word <hi rend="italic">elope</hi>,
               which means to go off, or to run off, and we should naturally say was gone off, but
                  <hi rend="italic">had</hi> run off. </p>
            <p>The nature of the subjunctive mood is dismissed in the same Letter without better
               success than has been obtained by former grammarians. An essay was published about
               thirty years ago in a periodical work,<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Diese
                  Quelle ließ sich nicht ermitteln. [FZ]</note> which brings the subject into a
               small compass; suggesting that the subjunctive mood ought always to be considered as
               a <hi rend="italic">conditional future</hi>. The examples given are, "If the Elbe <hi rend="italic">is now</hi> open, we shall soon have the mails, and <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, if there <hi rend="italic">be</hi> any news from the
               army, I will send it you immediately." "If Catiline <hi rend="italic">was</hi>
               generous, it was in order to serve his ambition." The subjunctive past, if I <hi rend="italic">were</hi>, becomes present, by being the future of the past; going
               back to the time when the present was future, and therefore contingent; and this
               conditional sense involves no difficulty, except when a mistaken adherence to the
               fancied rules of grammar forces it in where it has no business: thus the rules of
               some grammarians would lead us to say, if Catiline <hi rend="italic">were</hi>
               ambitious; which is totally contrary to the true sense of the subjunctive. <persName ref="wcobbett">Mr. Cobbett</persName> seems to have some such distinctions in view
               when he says that "<hi rend="italic">if</hi> has nothing at all to do with the
               government of the verb. It is the sense which governs." By this he means that if does
               not require a subjunctive unless it relates to a <hi rend="italic">future
                  contingency</hi>. He is right in saying "Though her chastity is becoming, it gives
               her no claim to praise:" but most decidedly wrong in adding "she would be criminal if
               she <hi rend="italic">was</hi> not chaste;" for <hi rend="italic">was</hi> is here
               used as relating to the present circumstances, which are the future of the past, and
               therefore require the subjunctive <hi rend="italic">were</hi> to denote the condition
               intended. He has, however, done signal justice to the cause of this injured verb, by
               introducing it for <hi rend="italic">was</hi>, in his sixth lesson, where he says it
               should have been "Your lordship <hi rend="italic">were</hi> apprized of every
               important circumstance." </p>
            <p>Such errors as this, however, are easily corrected, and many of the acute remarks
               which have been here copied are well worthy the attention of practical grammarians;
               at the same time enough has been said, without any disparagement of <persName ref="wcobbett">Cobbett</persName>’s talents, to show that a man cannot be well
               qualified to teach that which he has not had the means of properly learning. For
               although the English language appears at first sight to be extremely simple and
               philosophical in its structure, it has in fact been derived from a variety of
               heterogeneous sources; it has undergone a variety of vicissitudes, and has served for
               the expression of a multiplicity of discussions on the most refined subjects in
               literature and history and science, for the feelings of oratory, and the passions of
               poetry, and it has been worn away by degrees, as the crystal in the stream is worn to
               a pebble, till it has returned to a simplicity which wears the aspect of the
               immediate offspring of the Chinese or Egyptian or Mexican Hieroglyphics. But with all
               this, it has still some spots, some idioms, which invariable custom obliges us to
               retain; and which can only be distinguished from corruptions and vulgarisms by
               tracing their history through the different stages of its progress, including, of
               necessity, the corresponding idioms in the parent languages out of which it has
               arisen.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Believe me always, my dear Sir,<lb/>Your’s very sincerely,</salute>
               <signed>* * * *</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
