<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../WvH_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de"
     telota:doctype="wvh_letters">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wilhelm von Humboldt an Sir Alexander Johnston, 10.06.1828 ("An Essay on the
                    best Means of ascertaining the Affinities of Oriental Languages")<idno type="BBAW">1176</idno>
            </title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/135657458">Frank Zimmer</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/120492644">Jürgen Trabant</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/1053159110">Ute Tintemann</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Review
                    &amp; Editing</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6587-3353">Lou Klappenbach</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7447-4589">Sascha Grabsch</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data
                    curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Elise Hanrahan</persName>
               <resp ref="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <title>Wilhelm von Humboldt: Online-Edition der sprachwissenschaftlichen
                        Korrespondenz</title>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de"> Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der
                        Wissenschaften (BBAW) </ref>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative
                        Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="orig">Verschollen</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="print">Grundlage der Edition: Transactions of the Royal Asiatic
                            Society of Great Britain and Ireland II, 1830, S. 213–221</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="KMV">S. 212f.</bibl>
               </witness>
               <witness>
                  <bibl type="Mattson"/>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
            <listPerson type="mentioned">
               <person corresp="bgbabington">
                  <persName>Babington, Benjamin Guy</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="eburnouf">
                  <persName>Burnouf, Eugène</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="adcampbell">
                  <persName>Campbell, Alexander Duncan</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="htcolebrooke">
                  <persName>Colebrooke, Henry Thomas</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="fwellis">
                  <persName>Ellis, Francis Whyte</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="jmackintosh">
                  <persName>Mackintosh, Sir James</persName>
               </person>
               <person corresp="cmwhish">
                  <persName>Whish, Charles Matthew</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listBibl type="mentioned">
               <bibl corresp="870">Campbell, Alexander Duncan (1816): A grammar of the Teloogoo
                        language, commonly termed the Gentoo, peculiar to the indoos inhabiting the
                        north eastern provinces of the Indian peninsula, Madras: College
                        Press</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="936">Ellis, Francis Whyte (1810): Dissertation the second. On the
                        Malayálma language, Madras: College Press</bibl>
               <bibl corresp="1586">Mackintosh, Sir James (1806): Plan of a comparative
                        vocabulary of Indian languages: Read at the Literary Society of Bombay, on
                        the 26th May, 1806, Erstausgabe: Bombay; Reprint Calcutta: Hindoostanee
                        Press, 1808</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <ab type="incipit">SIR: / I have the honour to return you Sir James Mackintosh’s
                    interesting memoir …</ab>
         </abstract>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName key="wvh">Humboldt, Wilhelm von</persName>
               <date type="author" when="1828-06-10"/>
               <placeName key="London">London</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName key="ajohnston">Johnston, Sir Alexander</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <langUsage n="sa">
            <language ident="grc">Altgriechisch</language>
            <language ident="al">Amerikanische Sprachen (allgemein)</language>
            <language ident="map">Austronesische Sprachen (Südsee-Sprachen)</language>
            <language ident="eu">Baskisch</language>
            <language ident="de">Deutsch</language>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
            <language ident="got">Gotisch</language>
            <language ident="inc">Indische Sprachen</language>
            <language ident="kaw">Kawi</language>
            <language ident="la">Lateinisch</language>
            <language ident="lt">Litauisch</language>
            <language ident="ml">Malayalam</language>
            <language ident="mnc">Mandschurisch</language>
            <language ident="fa">Persisch</language>
            <language ident="sa">Sanskrit</language>
            <language ident="ta">Tamil</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <list>
            <item n="name">FZ</item>
            <item n="date">25. Oktober 2021</item>
            <item n="status">in Bearbeitung</item>
         </list>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url=""/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>SIR:<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Betitelt: "<bibl sameAs="664">An Essay on the best
                        Means of ascertaining the Affinities of Oriental Languages</bibl>, by Baron William
                        Humboldt, For. M.R.A.S. Contained in a Letter addressed to Sir Alexander
                        Johnston, Knt., V.P.R.A.S. Read June 14, 1828." – Der Brief, ursprünglich
                        auf Französisch verfasst, wurde von <persName ref="bgbabington">Benjamin Guy Babington</persName> ins Englische
                        übersetzt, und erschien unter dem englischen Titel in den <hi rend="italic">Transactions of
                        the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland</hi> des Jahres
                        1830. [FZ]</note>
            </opener>
            <p>I have the honour to return you <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James
                        Mackintosh</persName>’s <bibl sameAs="1586">interesting memoir</bibl>. It
                    possesses (like every thing which comes from the pen of that gifted and
                    ingenious writer) the highest interest; and the ideas which are so luminously
                    developed in it have the more merit, if we consider, that, at the period when
                        <bibl sameAs="1586">this memoir</bibl> was published, philosophical notions
                    on the study and nature of languages were rarer and more novel than they are at
                    present. </p>
            <p>I would, in the first place, observe, that the <orgName ref="14">Royal Asiatic
                        Society</orgName> could not direct its efforts to a point more important,
                    and more intimately connected with the national glory, than that of endeavouring
                    to throw further light on the relations which subsist among the different Indian
                    dialects. Since we cannot doubt that this part of Asia was the cradle of the
                    arts and sciences at an extremely remote period, it would be highly interesting
                    to ascertain with greater certainty whether the Sanscrit be a primitive idiom
                    belonging to those countries, or whether, on the contrary, as most of the
                    learned are at present inclined to believe, it was introduced as a foreign
                    language into India; and if so, the country whence it originated would naturally
                    follow in the course of inquiry. It is equally curious to determine whether the
                    primitive languages of India are to be traced over the Indian archipelago in
                    dialects differing little from each other, and whether we are to assign their
                    origin to these islands or to the continent. <persName ref="fwellis">Mr.
                        Ellis</persName>’s <bibl sameAs="936">paper on the Malayálam
                    language</bibl>, with which you were so good as to furnish me, contains
                    assertions on the affinity of the Tamul language to the idioms of Java, which it
                    would be very important to verify. </p>
            <p> It must be confessed that these problems are extremely difficult to solve; and
                    it is probable that we shall never arrive at results which are quite certain: we
                    should, however, carry these researches as far as possible, and the difficulty
                    of the undertaking ought not to deter, but rather to induce us to select the
                    most solid and certain means of insuring success. This is more particularly the
                    point to which I wish to direct your attention, since you have been pleased to
                    ask my opinion respecting the methods proposed by <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James Mackintosh</persName>. It would assuredly have been very
                    desirable to execute his plan, at the period when it was formed; we should then
                    by this time have had more complete information regarding the languages of
                    India; and should perhaps have been in the possession of dialects, of the
                    existence of which we are now ignorant. There do exist, however, some works,
                    such as <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James</persName> calls for. Not to
                    mention printed books, I have myself seen in the library of the <orgName ref="11">East-India Company</orgName> a MS. collection of Sanscrit words,
                    compared in great numbers with those of the other languages of India, made under
                    the direction of <persName ref="htcolebrooke">Mr. Colebrooke</persName>.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Anmerkung von Colebrooke (S. 221): "The work
                        to which allusion is made by Baron William de Humboldt, in the passage where
                        I am named, was undertaken by me in furtherance of the views developed by
                        Sir James Mackintosh. I thought that a more copious comparative vocabulary
                        than he had proposed, would be practically useful; and would be instructive
                        in more points of view than he had contemplated. Accordingly, at my
                        instance, a Sanscrit vocabulary and a Persian one were printed with blank
                        half pages, and distributed among gentlemen, whose situations were
                        considered to afford the opportunity of having the blank column filled up,
                        by competent persons, with a vocabulary of a provincial language.
                        Vocabularies of the same vernacular tongue by a Pandit and a Munshi, would
                        serve to correct mutually, and complete the information sought from them.
                        Very few answers, however, were received: indeed scarcely any, except from
                            <persName ref="fbhamilton">Dr. Buchanan Hamilton</persName>. The
                        compilation, to which Baron de Humboldt refers, comprises as many as I
                        succeeded in collecting. H.T.C."</note> Some distinguished authors, as for
                    instance <persName ref="adcampbell">Mr. Campbell</persName>, in <bibl sameAs="870">his Telugu Dictionary</bibl>, have been at pains to mark from
                    what foreign idiom such words are derived, as are not proper to the language of
                    which they form a part; and if these works do not embrace all the Indian idioms,
                    they have, on the other hand, the advantage of comprehending entire languages,
                    or at least of not being confined to a limited number of expressions. In the
                    present state of our knowledge of the languages of India, which is very
                    different from that of 1806, and possessing, as we now do, grammars and
                    dictionaries of most of these idioms, I should not advise our confining
                    ourselves to a plan which can only give a very imperfect idea of each of them.
                    We can, and ought, to go farther at the present day. I confess that I am
                    extremely averse to the system which proceeds on the supposition that we can
                    judge of the affinity of languages merely by a certain number of ideas expressed
                    in the different languages which we wish to compare. I beg you will not suppose,
                    however, that I am insensible to the value and utility of these comparisons: on
                    the contrary, when they are well executed, I appreciate all their importance;
                    but I can never deem them sufficient to answer the end for which they have been
                    undertaken; they certainly form a part of the data to be taken into account in
                    deciding on the affinity of languages, but we should never be guided by them
                    alone, if we wish to arrive at a solid, complete, and certain conclusion. If we
                    would make ourselves acquainted with the relation which subsists between two
                    languages, we ought to possess a thorough and profound knowledge of each of
                    them. This is a principle dictated alike by common sense and by that precision
                    acquired by the habit of scientific research. </p>
            <p>I do not mean to say, that, if we are unable to attain a profound knowledge of
                    each idiom, we should on this account entirely suspend our judgment: I only
                    insist on it that we should not prescribe to ourselves arbitrary limits, and
                    imagine that we are forming our judgment on a firm basis, while it is in reality
                    insufficient. </p>
            <p>The method of comparing a certain number of words of one existing language with
                    those of several others, has always the two-fold inconvenience of neglecting
                    entirely the grammatical relations, as if the grammar was not as essential a
                    part of the language as the words; and of taking from the language which we wish
                    to examine isolated words, selected, not according to their affinities and
                    natural etymology, but according to the ideas which they express. <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James Mackintosh</persName> very justly observes, that
                    the affinity of two languages is much better proved when whole families of words
                    resemble each other, than when this is the case with single words only. But how
                    shall we recognize families of words in foreign languages, if we only select
                    from them two or three hundred isolated terms? There undoubtedly subsists among
                    words of the same language an analogy of meanings and forms of combination easy
                    to be perceived. It is from this analogy, considered in its whole extent, and
                    compared with the analogy of the words of another language, that we discover the
                    affinity of two idioms, as far as it is recognizable in their vocabularies. It
                    is in this manner alone, that we recognize the roots and the methods by which
                    each language forms its derivatives. The comparison of two languages requires,
                    that we should examine whether, and in what degree, the roots and derivative
                    terms are common to both. It is not, then, by terms expressive of general ideas;
                    such as sun, moon, man, woman, &amp;c., that we must commence the comparison of
                    two languages, but by their entire dictionary critically explained. The simple
                    comparison of a certain number of words, by reducing the examination of
                    languages too much to a mere mechanical labour, often leads us to omit examining
                    sufficiently the words which form the subjects of our comparison: and to avoid
                    this defect, we are forced to enter deeply into all the minutiæ of grammar,
                    separating the words from their grammatical affixes, and comparing only what is
                    really essential to the expression of the idea which they represent. The words,
                    of which we seek a translation in different languages, often cannot be rendered
                    except by a compound term. Thus the sun in some languages is called the father,
                    the author, the star, &amp;c. of day. It is evident, that, in these cases, we no
                    longer compare the same words, but words altogether different. To conclude: it
                    is impossible to form a correct judgment on the resemblance of sounds without
                    having carefully studied the system of sounds of each of the languages which we
                    would compare. There occur often between different languages, and still more
                    frequently between different dialects, regular transformations of letters, by
                    which we can discover the identity of words that at first view seem to have but
                    a very slight resemblance in sound. On the other hand, a great resemblance of
                    sound in two words will sometimes prove nothing, or leave the judgment in great
                    uncertainty, if it be not supported by a train of analogies for the permutation
                    of the same letters. What I have remarked proves, as I think, that even if we
                    confine ourselves to the comparison of a certain number of words in different
                    languages, it is still necessary to enter more deeply into their structure, and
                    to apply ourselves to the study of their grammar. But further, I am quite
                    convinced that it is only by an accurate examination of the grammar of languages
                    that we can pronounce a decisive judgment on their true affinities. </p>
            <p>Languages are the true images of the modes in which nations think and combine
                    their ideas. The manner of this combination represented by the grammar, is
                    altogether as essential and characteristic as are the sounds applied to objects,
                    that is to say, the words. The form of language being quite inherent in the
                    intellectual faculties of nations, it is very natural that one generation should
                    transmit theirs to that which follows it; while words, being simple signs of
                    ideas, may be adopted by races altogether distinct. If I attach great
                    importance, however, under this view, to the grammar of a language, I do not
                    refer to the system of grammar in general, but to grammatical forms, considered
                    with respect to their system and their sounds taken conjointly. </p>
            <p>If two languages, such for instance as the Sanscrit and the Greek, exhibit
                    grammatical forms which are identical in arrangement, and have a close analogy
                    in their sounds, we have an incontestable proof that these two languages belong
                    to the same family. </p>
            <p>If, on the contrary, two languages do contain a great number of words in common,
                    but have no grammatical identity, their affinity becomes a matter of great
                    doubt; and if their grammars have, like those of the Basque and the Latin, an
                    essentially different character, these two languages certainly do not belong to
                    the same family. The words of the one have been merely transplanted into the
                    other, which has nevertheless retained its primitive forms. </p>
            <p>If I assert that, in order to prove the affinity of languages, we should pay
                    attention to the employment of grammatical forms and to their sounds taken
                    together, it is because I would affirm that they must be considered not only in
                    the abstract but in the concrete. Some examples will render this clearer. </p>
            <p>Several American languages have two plural forms in the first person, an
                    exclusive and an inclusive form, according as we would include or exclude the
                    person addressed. It has been thought that this peculiarity belonged exclusively
                    to the American languages; but it is also found in the Mantchu, the Tamul, and
                    in all the dialects of the South Sea Islands. All these languages have indeed
                    this grammatical form in common; but it is only in the abstract. Each of them
                    expresses it by a different sound: the identity of this form, therefore, does
                    not furnish any proof of the affinity of these languages. </p>
            <p>On the other hand, the Sanscrit infinitive, or rather the affixes <foreign sameAs="sa" n="transEd">tuṃ<graphic url="Rosen/Rosen-WvH_1829_01_09/0878.svg"/>
               </foreign> and <foreign sameAs="sa" n="transEd">tu<graphic url="Rosen/Rosen-WvH_1829_01_09/0879.svg"/>
               </foreign>, as in <foreign sameAs="sa" n="transEd">jetukāma<graphic url="Rosen/Rosen-WvH_1829_01_09/0880.svg"/>
               </foreign>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Hier korrekt, im Sonderdruck von 1828 (und
                        einem Teil der bereits gedruckten Auflage) als <graphic url="Johnston/06.svg"/>. Zur Korrektur siehe auch <ref type="link" target="55">den Brief</ref> von <persName ref="farosen">Friedrich August
                            Rosen</persName> an Wilhelm von Humboldt vom <date when="1829-01-09">9.
                            Januar 1829</date> und den Errata-Zusatz auf S. XII im 1830 vollständig
                        gedruckt vorliegenden Band der <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi>.
                        [FZ]</note> „desirous of vanquishing,“ correspond as grammatical forms with
                    the Latin <hi rend="italic">supines</hi>, and there is at the same time a
                    perfect identity of sound in these forms in the two languages, as the Latin <hi rend="italic">supines</hi> terminate invariably in <hi rend="italic">tum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tu</hi>. The striking conformity of the
                    Sanscrit auxiliary verb to that of the Greek and Lithuanian languages, has been
                    ingeniously developed by <persName ref="bopp">Professor Bopp</persName>. The
                    Sanscrit <foreign n="transEd" sameAs="sa">veda<graphic url="Johnston/04.svg"/>
               </foreign>, the Greek <foreign sameAs="grc">οἶδα</foreign>, and the Gothic
                        <hi rend="italic">vait</hi>, are evidently of the same origin. In all these
                    three words there is a conformity both of sound and signification: but further;
                    all the three verbal forms have these two peculiarities in common, that though
                    preterites, they are used in a present sense, and that in all three the <hi rend="italic">short</hi> radical vowel, which is retained in the plural, is
                    changed to a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> vowel in the singular. The Lithuanian
                        <hi rend="italic">weizdmi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I know</hi> , and the
                    Sanscrit <foreign n="transEd" sameAs="sa">veidma<graphic url="Johnston/05.svg"/>
               </foreign>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Hier korrekt, im Sonderdruck
                        von 1828 als <graphic url="Johnston/07.svg"/>.</note>, shew clearly at first
                    view that this word is not only the same in the two languages (as <hi rend="italic">bos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">beef</hi> in Latin and
                    English), but that the two languages have, in the termination <hi rend="italic">mi</hi>, modelled these words on the same grammatical form; for they not
                    only mark the persons of the verb by inflexions added to the end of the root,
                    but the affix of the first person singular is in both cases the syllable <hi rend="italic">mi</hi>. </p>
            <p>There is then in the examples adduced a conformity in grammatical use, and at the
                    same time in sound; and it is impossible to deny that the languages which
                    possess these forms must be of the same family. </p>
            <p>The difference between the real affinity of languages, which presumes a filiation
                    as it were among the nations who speak them, and that degree of relation which
                    is purely historical, and only indicates temporary and accidental connexions
                    among nations, is, in my opinion, of the greatest importance. Now it appears to
                    me impossible ever to ascertain that difference merely by the examination of
                    words; especially, if we examine but a small number of them. </p>
            <p>It is perhaps too much to assert, that words pass from age to age and from nation
                    to nation; that they arise also from connexions (which though secret, are common
                    to all men) between sounds and objects, and that they thus establish a certain
                    identity between all languages; while the manner of casting and arranging these
                    words, that is to say, the grammar, constitutes the particular differences of
                    dialects. This assertion, I repeat, is perhaps too bold, when expressed in this
                    general way; yet I am strongly inclined to consider it correct, provided the
                    expression <hi rend="italic">grammar</hi> be not taken vaguely, but with a due
                    regard to the sounds of grammatical forms. But whatever opinion may be
                    entertained with respect to this manner of considering the difference of
                    languages, it appears to me at all events demonstrated: </p>
            <p>First, that all research into the affinity of languages, which does not enter
                    quite as much into the examination of the grammatical system as into that of
                    words, is faulty and imperfect; and, </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the proofs of the real affinity of languages, that is to say, the
                    question whether two languages belong to the same family, ought to be
                    principally deduced from the grammatical system, and can be deduced from that
                    alone; since the identity of words only proves a resemblance such as may be
                    purely historical and accidental. </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James Mackintosh</persName> rejects the
                    examination of grammar, for this reason, that languages which are evidently of
                    the same stock have very different grammars. But we must not be misled by this
                    phenomenon, although it is in itself quite true. The grammatical form of
                    languages depends, on the one hand, it is true, upon the nature of these
                    languages; but it also depends, on the other hand, upon the changes which they
                    experience in the course of ages, and in consequence of historical revolutions.
                    Out of these changes it has arisen, that languages of the same family have a
                    different grammatical system, and that languages really distinct resemble each
                    other in some degree. But the slightest examination will suffice to shew the
                    real relations which subsist between those languages, especially if by following
                    the plan above laid down we proceed to the examination of forms which are alike
                    identical in their uses and in their sounds. It is thus that we discover without
                    difficulty that the English language is of Germanic origin, and that the Persian
                    belongs to the Sanscrit family of languages, notwithstanding the very great
                    difference which exists between the grammars of these idioms. </p>
            <p>It is generally believed, that the affinity of two languages is undeniably
                    proved, if words that are applied to objects which must have been known to the
                    natives ever since their existence, exhibit a great degree of resemblance, and
                    to a certain extent this is correct. But, notwithstanding this, such a method of
                    judging of the affinity of languages seems to me by no means infallible. It
                    often happens, that even the objects of our earliest perceptions, or of the
                    first necessity, are represented by words taken from foreign languages, and
                    which belong to a different class. If we only examine the list furnished by
                        <persName ref="jmackintosh">Sir James Mackintosh</persName>, we shall find
                    there such words as <hi rend="italic">people</hi>, <hi rend="italic">countenance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">touch</hi>, <hi rend="italic">voice</hi>, <hi rend="italic">labour</hi>, <hi rend="italic">force</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">power</hi>, <hi rend="italic">marriage</hi>, <hi rend="italic">spirit</hi>, <hi rend="italic">circle</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tempest</hi>, <hi rend="italic">autumn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">time</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">mountain</hi>, <hi rend="italic">valley</hi>, <hi rend="italic">air</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vapour</hi>, <hi rend="italic">herb</hi>, <hi rend="italic">verdure</hi>, and others of the same kind. Now
                    all these words being evidently derived from the Latin, as it was transformed
                    after the fall of the Roman empire, we ought, judging from these words, rather
                    to assign to the English an origin similar to that of the Roman languages than
                    to that of the German. </p>
            <p>If what I have here advanced be well founded, it appears to me easy to point out
                    the system which the <orgName ref="14">Royal Asiatic Society</orgName> would do
                    well to pursue, in order to complete our knowledge of the Indian languages, and
                    to resolve the grand problem which they present to the minds of philologists who
                    endeavour to discover the origin and the filiation of languages. </p>
            <p>It would be proper to commence by examining the country geographically, taking a
                    review of every part of India, in order to know exactly in what parts we are
                    still in want of sufficient materials to determine the nature of their idioms.
                    Where deficiencies are discovered, efforts should be used for their supply, by
                    encouraging those persons who are already employed on those languages, or may
                    intend studying them, to form grammars and dictionaries, and to publish the
                    principal works existing in these languages, for which every facility should be
                    afforded them. If materials to a certain extent were thus collected, we should
                    unquestionably not want men who would be able to deduce from them conclusions
                    from which to prepare a critical view of the affinity of the Indian languages,
                    and to determine, as far as the data which we might possess would admit, the
                    manner in which the Sanscrit and other languages of India and its islands have
                    reciprocally acted upon each other. I assume that the learned of the Continent
                    would take their share in this work, <persName ref="eburnouf">M. E.
                        Burnouf</persName>, of <placeName ref="Paris">Paris</placeName>, having
                    already commenced a series of papers on the subject in the <hi rend="italic">Nouveau Journal Asiatique</hi>. </p>
            <p>There exists in England a vast quantity of manuscript materials relating to these
                    languages. <persName ref="bgbabington">Dr. B. Babington</persName>, for
                    instance, possesses alphabets altogether unknown in Europe up to the present
                    time. In England, also, the great advantage is possessed of being able to direct
                    works upon these languages to be undertaken in India itself, and to guide such
                    labours by plans sent from this country. In India these are living languages,
                    and literary men of the very nations in which they are spoken may be employed in
                    the researches we wish to forward. No other nation possesses so valuable an
                    advantage. It is important to profit by it. The deficiencies in our knowledge
                    are numerous and evident. We possess scarcely any thing upon the Malayalim; and
                    are in want of a printed dictionary of the Tamul. But while we keep this object
                    strictly in view, and work upon a fixed plan, we shall insensibly fill up these
                    vacancies. It is certainly difficult to find men who both can and will engage in
                    a work like this, but they are undoubtedly to be found. Thus <persName ref="bgbabington">Dr. Babington</persName> has mentioned <persName ref="cmwhish">Mr. Whish</persName>
               <note type="footnote" resp="editor">Charles Matthew Whish (1794–1833), englischer ziviler Angestellter in der
                        Madras-Niederlassung der East India Company. [FZ]</note> to me, as being
                    profoundly acquainted with the Malayalim, and as being already employed in
                    making it better known in Europe. Solid labours upon languages are, in their
                    nature, slow. In an enterprize so vast as that of examining to the utmost
                    possible extent each of the numerous languages of India, progress can only be
                    made insensibly and step by step. But learned societies afford this advantage,
                    that the same labour can be continued through a long series of years; and
                    complete and perfect works upon two or three idioms are certainly preferable to
                    notions, more or less superficial, upon all the dialects of India, hastily put
                    forth for the purpose of coming at once to a general conclusion. </p>
            <p>These, Sir, are my ideas upon the subject, upon which you wished to have my
                    opinion. It is only in compliance with your request, that I have ventured to lay
                    them before you; for I am well aware how much better able the distinguished
                    members of the <orgName ref="14">Royal Asiatic Society</orgName> are to form a
                    judgment of, and give an opinion upon, this matter than I am. </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I request you, Sir, to accept the assurance of my highest
                        respect.</salute>
               <signed>(Signed) Humboldt.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>London,
                        June 10, 1828.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
